Guide to the National Association of College and University Chaplains and Directors of Religious Life Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
National Association of College and University Chaplains and Directors of Religious Life Records
1947-2014
RG 167
Yale University Divinity School Library
2.5
5 boxes
Administrative records, publications, and conference records document the work of the National Association of College and University Chaplains. The National Association of College and University Chaplains and Directors of Religious Life (NACUC) is the interfaith professional community of chaplains, rabbis, deans of chapel, and other personnel appointed by academic institutions to be responsible for the religious program of the academic community. It was founded in a national conference convened by Clarence Shedd which met at Yale University in 1948. Since then, NACUC has met annually throughout the country.
National Association of College and University Chaplains
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of NACUC.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
NACUC was founded in 1948 at a conference convened by Clarence Shedd at Yale University. Since that time, the NACUC expanded to include a membership of 121 chaplains by 1996. It holds annual conferences throughout the country. The organization went through a variety of affiliations with other professional organizations of chaplains/religious leaders. The NACUC is directed by a president (a revolving position) and an executive committee. A high mark of the NACUC was the 50th anniversary conference, "Holy Wilderness" held at Yale University June 27-July 2, 1998.
Throughout its history the NACUC published a regular newsletter. Beginning in 1998 it also published a news journal called Ailanthus at irregular intervals.
The NACUC Information Service was started in 1959 with the intention of helping clergy find places at colleges and universities. Bradford S. Abernethy, University Chaplain at Rutgers University, ran this service, gathering personal data forms from interested clergy members and sending them to colleges and universities that were seeking to employ a chaplain or other religious leader. The service was discontinued in 1961 because Abernethy found it difficult to learn of openings at colleges.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the material is in Series I, Administrative Records, which contains minutes, correspondence, financial and legal records, and other materials related to the history and operations of NACUC. Series II contains newsletters and the Ailanthus news journal. Series III documents conferences of NACUC, with the largest amount of material related to the 1998 conference that was held at Yale.
Series IV contains forms submitted to NACUC's Information Service program by clergy who were seeking college and university chaplain positions. These forms were transferred from the Records of the University Chaplain (Bradford S. Abernethy) collection at Rutgers in 2006.
Series V is an addendum containing documentation up through 2014.
Arrangement
I. Administrative Records, 1947-2004
II. Newsletters, 1948-2003
III. Annual Conferences, 1962-2005
IV. Information Service Program, 1959-1961
V: Addendum, 1990-2014
Universities and colleges -- Religion; Clergy; National Association of College and University Chaplains
- Administrative Records, 1947-2004; Series I
  - Founding correspondence between Sidney Lovett and Clarence Shedd; press release re. Chaplain Gordon Shea's death, 1947-1951, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Fifty Years of Chaplaincy: NACUC 1948-1998" by Donovan Hull; "Bits of History: 1948-1975"; Religion in Higher Education note on Chaplaincy, 1948-1998, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Registration/Membership Lists, 1964-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Booklets on Gathering, Programs, Leadership, Members, Lifetime Members, 1948-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Constitution; Reports/resolutions from conferences and consultations, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - By-Laws, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 2001-2004 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Tax Exempt Status, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Executive Committee / Business meetings, incl. financial reports, 1967-2001 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Executive Committee / Business meetings, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Executive Committee / Business meeting, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Professional Relations Committee: Questionnaire re. Relationship of the chaplain to the college; Reports, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Standards and Guidelines; Evaluation of chaplains; Evaluations and job descriptions, 1972-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Coordinating Council of the Professional Religious Associations in Higher Education (CCPRAHE), 1970, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Regional Affairs Meetings, 1966-1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - NACUC-Related papers, articles and resolutions, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - NACUC-Related papers, articles and resolutions, incl. undated material, 1968-1994 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Various brochures (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous: re.the National Campus Ministry Association; Campus Ministry Resources (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Publications, 1948-2003; Series II
  - Newsletters, 1948-1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Newsletters, 1973-1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Newsletters, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Newsletters, 1987-2002 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Newsletters, 1998-2003 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Ailanthus News Journal, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Ailanthus News Journal, 1990, 1995, 1997, 2001, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Ailanthus News Journal, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Conferences, 1962-2005; Series III
  - Miscellaneous annual meetings: minutes and brochures, 1962-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 19th Annual Conference, Northwestern University,1966, 1966 Apr 11-14 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "Holy Wilderness" conference, at Yale: Participants, 1998, June 27-July 2 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Holy Wilderness": Publicity, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Holy Wilderness": Misc pre-conference resources: First Things article on homosexuality; correspondence with David Maitland, 1995, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "Holy Wilderness": Keynote addresses: "Holy Wilderness: Professional and Religious work on Campuses" by Diana Chapman Walsh; "After Egypt: Sign Posts of Faith in Postmodern Wilderness" by Dr. Nancy Ammerman; "Rise of Conservatism in its Various Forms" by Dr. Riffat Hassan, 1998 - June 29, July 1 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Holy Wilderness": Welcome Speech, Text Study, 50 Years of Chaplaincy, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Holy Wilderness": Multifaith Worship, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "Holy Wilderness": Budget and Finances, including Knutson grant, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "Holy Wilderness": Follow-up: Evaluation forms; Thank you notes; Continuing Ed Equivalency forms; resulting publicity, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "Holy Wilderness": Photos, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Mosaic of Faith" conference, Atlanta, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "The Spirituality of Identity: Gender and Sexuality" conference, San Antonio, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Information Service Program, 1959-1961; Series IV
  - Register of personal data forms; letters from Bradford Abernethy explaining demise of the program, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Personal data forms # 1- 83, with cards attached showing institutions to which they were sent, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 46-48)
- Addendum, 1990-2016; Series V
  - By-Laws and Constitution revisions, 2000-2011 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - NACUC history, 1990-2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee and Annual Meeting minutes, 1999-2003 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee and Annual Meeting minutes, 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee and Annual Meeting minutes, 2006-2007 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee and Annual Meeting minutes, 2008-2009 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee and Annual Meeting minutes, 2010-2011 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee and Annual Meeting minutes, 2012-2014 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Conference materials, 1997-2003 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Conference materials, 2004-2011 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - NACUC Newsletter, 1998-2003 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Membership lists, 2005-2011 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Budgets, 1998-2011 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN conference: schedule, list of attendees; February Business Meeting and Executive Board Meeting notes; Summer Executive Board Meeting notes, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Furman University, Greenville, SC conference: schedule, list of attendees; Title IX session presentation; February Business meeting notes; Journal proposal; February Executive Board meeting notes; Summer Executive Board meeting notes, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 15)